Hey everyone, and thanks for jumping
back into the heavy metal verse.
Today, we're going to talk about gold,
and we're going to be discussing the
next big move. If you guys like the
content, make sure you subscribe to the
channel, give the video a thumbs up, and
also to make sure you get your ticket to
the first ITC conference, Investing
Through the Cycles conference, taking
place in November. Link is in the
description below or the pinned comment.
Obviously, gold will be a theme of the
conference, and hopefully, I will see
you guys there. Ticket prices are going
up on September 1st,
uh probably the evening of September
1st, just to give you a little bit more
time, but they are going to be going up.
So, if you are planning on coming, make
sure you go ahead and get your ticket.
Let's go ahead and jump in. So, we've
talked a lot about gold on the channel,
really going all the way back to 2019,
right? I mean, some of the first videos
I did were were about gold all the way
back then.
And, you know, my general assessment of
of gold is that we have had, you know,
we had sort of an initial move way back
in the day, right? I mean, talking about
2016, 2017, that feels like back in the
day now. Um and then we had sort of a
consolidation period through 2022.
And then another move up, and I think
we're just in a sort of a second
consolidation period in 2026.
I am still a believer in the actual top
for gold is still ahead of us. That is
what I think, and I'll I'll talk a
little bit about like what would
invalidate that view, but that is my
base case right now. I think that
geopolitical uncertainty is only going
to go up. Uh central banks around the
world are only going to likely continue
to add gold uh to, you know, to to what
they're buying. And I also think,
frankly, that, you know, at the end of
the day, when push comes to shove, they
will print, and I think things like gold
will also benefit from that. So,
I want to talk about though the short
term. Because if you guys go back and
look at the videos we did on gold
earlier in the year, well, and and
especially last year, we said to expect
a correction in gold starting in early
2026, right? Early 2026. You can see
that gold rallied into about February.
Now, it's down a decent amount, right?
Like it dropped about 30%, but 30% drops
by gold,
they're normal. I mean, in fact, they're
not even all that bad compared to some
of the drops that we've previously had.
If you were to look at the gold bull
market from the 2000s, during the '08
crisis, gold dropped about 33 and 1/2%.
If you go back even further to the bull
market we had in the 1970s going into
the 1980s, there was a a drawdown in
gold of almost 50%. So, a 30% drop
really isn't that archaic of a drop to
then say that you can't have a
continuation of the bull market. I think
the bull market will likely continue,
but we are in a in a pullback at the
current time. So,
let me let me go through what I think's
happening, all right?
Gold has had a pullback, right?
Throughout a lot of 2026. This low that
gold just put in in the summer, you
should know on average, that is when in
terms of time, that is when gold often
finds a low in midterm years. So, if you
were to look at the year-to-date ROI of
gold in midterm years, this is 2026.
Now, what we're going to do is we're
going to look at the average
of all prior midterm years going back to
19 the 1970s.
And what you'll notice is that on
average, gold tends to start the year
off strong. It then finds
a period of weakness going into the
summer, but on average gold bottoms in
early July, right? Like late June, early
July timeframe.
And that's exactly where gold found a
low, and it started moving up. Now, what
do I think's happening, right? What do I
think? We've talked about this.
I think that cuz you might you might
notice that gold actually had a pullback
the last couple of weeks. This is
actually very much in line with how gold
normally plays out in a midterm years.
Like there's there's usually a low in
the summer, a rally out of it, and then
a one pullback, one final pullback
before then theoretically gold would
then run again.
Okay? Now,
if you were to look at just the last two
midterm years,
2022 and 2018, you can see that gold did
not find its like yearly low until like
late September, October timeframe. So,
I do want to leave some room for that
outcome, but
that's not necessarily like my base case
right now. I what I'm looking for is for
gold to print
likely a higher low
in like late September, early October.
Could be a lower low, but I I I think
that sort of the rationale for saying a
lower low would just be saying, "Well,
it has to follow 2018 and 2022." But it
doesn't, right? I mean, if you were to
look at other bull markets, notably the
one from 1974, you can see that gold
started off strong, it faded, bottomed
in the summer, moved up, correction in
the late September, early October, and
it was at new all-time highs by by the
holidays, right? So, by by the sort of
the end of the year.
Now, look at the chart. Like look at
gold.
Look at 1974 cuz this is an example we
actually compared it to back in like a
year ago, essentially.
Um
look at 1974. Gold had a big move up
into March in March and April. Had, by
the way, from that high
almost a 30% drop.
Rallied off the low
about 20% a little less than 20% and
then it had a pullback into
mid-September where it formed a higher
low and then went to a higher high.
So
if you go look at gold here in
um
2026, right? About a 30% drop. How far
of a rally off the low? About 20%. We're
now getting that pullback. I think what
I'd be looking for here
I'd be looking for gold to likely print
a higher low.
Okay? I I think it'll be a higher low.
If it's a lower low, it does not mean
that the bull market is necessarily
over. Okay? It does not. I know there's
the the main discussion right now is to
whether this top right here in January
is like the top or if if we can get
another move. Now, there's a lot of
people that think it's the secular top,
right? Like that it'll be the top for
the next 20 to 30 years.
I'm not in that camp admittedly, but
my invalidation on that
would be if gold is not really breaking
out by about mid-2027,
then I would at that point have to
reconsider my position. I think about
mid-2027 at the latest would be how long
it should take for gold to start putting
in new all-time highs. And I I think it
could happen as early as later this
year, especially if we want to follow
the 1974 playbook. Now, you might be
asking like what what's the like what's
the reason for you know for a potential
gold pullback, right? Like does it have
to happen? Well, what I think is the
most likely reason for a pullback in
gold is a very brief research resurgence
in the US dollar currency index, the
dollar, the DXY, the Dixie, if you will.
And where that comes from, if you look
at presidential return um
or sorry, president presidential term
return paths
and if you look at the dollar right? If
you pull up the dollar and and we simply
look at how the dollar has performed
under Trump's second term compared to
his first term, it's been almost a
carbon copy and it can and we we
followed this. I mean, in fact, in 2025,
I said expect the dollar to go down for
a year, form a base and start
begrudgingly going higher into the
midterm year. And you know, this
pullback that we've had while a lot of
people might equate it to the reason for
the pullback would be what Bessent said
or you know, whatever, we also had a
similar pullback around this time in
Trump's first term in the in the first
time he had he went through a midterm
year. And what you'll notice is that
there was one where there was another
final push by the dollar to the upside
before the end of the year. Now, I think
the reason why the dollar will get that
surge back up to the upside before the
end of the year is because we are very
likely going to see one or two rate cuts
or sorry, rate hikes before the end of
the year. You can already see the
market's pricing in
a couple of rate hikes potentially
before the end of the year. I think
that's going to provide some strength to
the dollar before this year is over. I
think that's what's going to have gold
remaining weak in the very, very short
term and I when I say very, very short
term, I just mean for like, you know,
two to four weeks. I'm not talking
about, you know, very long here. I think
it's going to be short-lived weakness.
And and then from there, I think gold
will get another move up. Now, if you
look at the bull market support band for
gold, remember, this is based on monthly
moving averages, not weekly. You can see
that it it didn't even quite tag its
bull market support band.
But that's normal. Like through a lot of
the prior bull markets that gold's been
in, a lot of times it it doesn't always
tag it. Like sometimes it'll come close,
but it it doesn't always have to tag it
before continuing up. You can see that
happened throughout the 2000s. And then
also if you look closely through the
1970s, there were plenty of times where
it would get really, really close to
tagging it, but it wouldn't quite get
there.
So,
I I think that
gold from here
will likely in the short term experience
weakness going into like mid-September
or maybe even mid-October at the latest.
It'll likely be caused by the dollar
going up.
But I think that gold will likely print
a higher low
in like mid-September or mid-October,
like a a higher low.
And then from there go back up.
If it prints a lower low, I still
wouldn't give up on the idea, right?
Like yes, it's possible that you have a
slightly lower low. Um but I I wouldn't
I wouldn't make that sort of like the
baseline expectation. I suppose the
lower low would be like if it were to be
back testing this trend line or
something, right? Like maybe in that
case, you you come back down and you
sweep the low from June.
And and in that case, you would actually
be following 2018 and 2022 where the low
occurs in September-October. So, I I
don't want to make the case that it
can't happen. What I would say is this,
I'd say I'd put about a
uh maybe about a 65% chance that it's a
higher low and about a 35% chance that
it's a lower low. But regardless of what
it is, I I think that gold would have a
strong bounce of that low going into the
end of the year. That is my assessment
of what gold is likely going to do. Uh I
know some of you guys have been on this
journey with me with gold for a long
time.
So, let's see if this can if if this
does in fact play out. And and if it
does, then I think we're looking at
another good year for gold in 2027. If
you look at
If we look at the year-to-date ROI, I
mean, we obviously spend a lot of time
looking at it in the midterm year cuz
that's what we're in. But, if you
actually look at gold in um
uh in
Sorry, let me pull this back up.
If you look at This is not the right
one. If you look at gold in
pre-having years, right? Or I guess you
could call it a a pre-election year, uh
if you will.
Um normally, it it actually does tend to
do pretty well in uh
in pre-election years. So, I guess we
just re-updated all this stuff, so it's
not I guess we'll just go with this one
for now. But, I mean, basically the
idea, right, is if you look at at 2026,
you can see this move. Now, if you look
at it in
2023,
gold generally trended up. If you look
at it in, say, 2019, generally trended
up. 2015, it was slightly down. Uh but,
2011 was up. 2007 was up.
2003 was up, right? I mean, a lot of the
pre-election years, gold does generally
trend higher.
So,
let's see if that actually plays out. I
I think it likely will, uh but, you got
to form the low first.
Uh likely a higher low, potentially a
lower low in mid-September to
mid-October. And from there, I think
there's a good chance gold will be back
in business. If you guys like the
content, make sure you subscribe to the
channel, give the video a thumbs up. And
as a reminder, if you would like to talk
about this stuff in person, uh you can
get your ticket to the first Investing
Through the Cycles Conference taking
place in Miami. Main conference day will
be November 21st. We'll have some stuff.
Um especially on the day before that.
So, make sure you guys get your ticket.
We're about to raise prices here on
September 1st. So, if you are wanting to
go, go ahead and get your ticket. Thank
you guys for being here. I'll see you
next time. Bye.